<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-06-10T22:42:54-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/feed.xml</id><title type="html">2025S, UCLA CS269 Course Projects</title><subtitle>Course projects for UCLA CS269, Seminar on AI Agents and Foundation Models</subtitle><author><name>UCLAdeepvision</name></author><entry><title type="html">Pretraining Multilingual Foundation Models</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/2025/06/10/student-29-30-pretraining-multilingual.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pretraining Multilingual Foundation Models" /><published>2025-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/2025/06/10/student-29-30-pretraining-multilingual</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/2025/06/10/student-29-30-pretraining-multilingual.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Multilingual pretraining in large language models (LLMs) may confer cognitive benefits similar to those observed in multilingual humans, including enhanced reasoning and cross-linguistic generalization. Models often learn better when exposed to linguistic diversity rather than monolingual data, but the optimal balance remains unclear. In this study, we systematically investigate the impact of multilingual exposure by training LLaMA 3.2-1B models on varying ratios of English-Chinese data, characterize the performance changes across multiple benchmarks, and find that 25% multilingual exposure yields optimal results—improving logical reasoning and code synthesis by up to 130% while preventing catastrophic forgetting, though with some trade-offs in fairness metrics.</p>
</blockquote>

<!--more-->
<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#introduction" id="markdown-toc-introduction">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#related-work" id="markdown-toc-related-work">Related Work</a></li>
  <li><a href="#experimental-design" id="markdown-toc-experimental-design">Experimental Design</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#model-and-pretraining" id="markdown-toc-model-and-pretraining">Model and Pretraining</a></li>
      <li><a href="#language-splits" id="markdown-toc-language-splits">Language Splits</a></li>
      <li><a href="#data-source-and-preprocessing" id="markdown-toc-data-source-and-preprocessing">Data Source and Preprocessing</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#evaluation" id="markdown-toc-evaluation">Evaluation</a></li>
  <li><a href="#results" id="markdown-toc-results">Results</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#optimal-split" id="markdown-toc-optimal-split">Optimal Split</a></li>
      <li><a href="#benchmark-performance" id="markdown-toc-benchmark-performance">Benchmark Performance</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion" id="markdown-toc-conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
  <li><a href="#references" id="markdown-toc-references">References</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p>Human multilingualism is widely associated with enhanced cognitive flexibility, improved executive control, and a broadened conceptual repertoire [1,2]. Languages encode distinct semantic frameworks and cultural logics, granting multilingual individuals access to diverse cognitive strategies [3]. Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have prompted the question of whether similar benefits can emerge in artificial systems through multilingual pretraining.</p>

<p>Transformer-based LLMs have demonstrated strong performance across a wide spectrum of reasoning, generation, and inference tasks [4,5]. However, the potential impact of multilingual training on their cognitive alignment and generalization capacity remains underexplored. This work investigates whether multilingual exposure confers systematic benefits to LLMs in reasoning, fairness, and cross-linguistic generalization, and whether these effects are comparable to the cognitive advantages observed in multilingual humans.</p>

<p>Specifically, we examine whether multilingual pretraining improves logical and cognitive reasoning, introduces emergent capabilities relative to monolingual baselines, mitigates social bias, and enhances generalization to low-resource languages. We further address disparities in language representation by comparing the effects of multilingualism across high- and low-resource settings under matched data and model conditions.</p>

<h2 id="related-work">Related Work</h2>

<p>Multilingual pretraining has shown strong empirical gains across cross-lingual transfer, zero-shot inference, and comprehension tasks [6,7]. Studies such as “Language Models as Multilingual Chain-of-Thought Reasoners” [6] demonstrate that multilingual LLMs can engage in structured reasoning across multiple languages, often outperforming monolingual models on tasks requiring abstraction and inference. Bandarkar et al. introduced the Belebele benchmark, revealing systematic gains in comprehension for MLLMs exposed to linguistic diversity [7].</p>

<p>The underlying mechanism is often attributed to <strong>cross-lingual knowledge transfer</strong>, wherein shared representations across languages allow models to generalize from high-resource to low-resource settings. Large-scale parallel corpora, such as WikiMatrix [8] and the UN Parallel Corpus [9], have been instrumental in supporting these findings. Further, reinforcement learning and instruction-tuning methods have revealed emergent capabilities in multilingual settings [5], analogous to transfer learning and conceptual blending in human cognition [1,2].</p>

<p>Despite these advances, key open questions remain. In particular, it is unclear to what extent the observed gains are attributable to multilingualism itself, rather than confounding factors such as total data scale, domain overlap, or token distribution. Furthermore, continual pretraining techniques—though widely adopted—have not been systematically evaluated in multilingual contexts for their impact on reasoning or fairness.</p>

<p>Our work seeks to isolate the causal effect of multilingual exposure under controlled conditions. We pretrain LLaMA 3.2–1B models on a balanced parallel corpus using carefully tuned sampling ratios and evaluate them on standard benchmarks for reasoning, fairness, and multilingual generalization.</p>

<h2 id="experimental-design">Experimental Design</h2>

<h3 id="model-and-pretraining">Model and Pretraining</h3>

<p>We use the LLaMA 3.2–1B architecture, a compact, decoder-only transformer model pretrained primarily on English. All models are trained from the same initialization using full-parameter finetuning and identical hyperparameters. Pretraining is conducted using DeepSpeed (Stage 3), with 1 epoch over our custom multilingual datasets, employing gradient checkpointing and fused AdamW optimization.</p>

<div class="language-yaml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="na">model_name_or_path</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">meta-llama/Llama-3.2-1B</span>
<span class="na">learning_rate</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">2e-5</span>
<span class="na">num_train_epochs</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="m">1.0</span>
<span class="na">cutoff_len</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="m">2048</span>
<span class="na">gradient_accumulation_steps</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="m">8</span>
<span class="na">per_device_train_batch_size</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="m">8</span>
<span class="na">warmup_ratio</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="m">0.15</span>
<span class="na">lr_scheduler_type</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">cosine</span>
<span class="na">bf16</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="no">true</span>
<span class="na">tf32</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="no">true</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>This consistent configuration ensures that observed differences in performance can be attributed to variations in multilingual exposure rather than architectural or training changes.</p>

<h3 id="language-splits">Language Splits</h3>

<p>We divide our training data into two sets:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>High-resource (Set A)</th>
      <th>Low-resource (Set B)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Chinese (zh)</td>
      <td>Farsi (fa)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Hindi (hi)</td>
      <td>Swahili (sw)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Arabic (ar)</td>
      <td>Bengali (bn)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Spanish (es)</td>
      <td>Yoruba (yo)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Set A consists of widely resourced languages with substantial parallel corpora. Set B comprises lower-resourced languages with less digital representation. This division allows us to assess the differential impact of multilingual training across language strata.</p>

<h3 id="data-source-and-preprocessing">Data Source and Preprocessing</h3>

<p>We use the ParaCrawl English–Chinese v1.0 dataset [10], a large-scale, web-mined corpus with approximately 14 million aligned sentence pairs. ParaCrawl was selected for its breadth of domains, sentence-level alignment quality, and scalability, avoiding the domain-specific biases present in datasets like CCAligned [12] or OpenSubtitles [13].</p>

<p>To explore the impact of multilingual exposure, we construct five variants of the training data by varying the proportion of Chinese-to-English examples (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">zh_ratio</code> ∈ {0.0, 0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1.0}). This controls for total dataset size and domain while modulating language diversity:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">zh_ratio = 0.0</code>: Monolingual English</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">zh_ratio = 0.25–0.75</code>: Mixed bilingual</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">zh_ratio = 1.0</code>: Monolingual Chinese</li>
</ul>

<p>Each sample is selected with the specified probability from the aligned pair. All examples are filtered for language quality, deduplicated, and converted to JSON format compatible with LLaMA-Factory’s pretraining pipeline [14].</p>

<h2 id="evaluation">Evaluation</h2>

<p>We evaluate all models on a suite of tasks probing logical reasoning, fairness, common sense, and multilingual understanding. Our benchmarks include:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Logical Reasoning:</strong> GSM8K [15], MATH [16], HumanEval [17], GPQA Diamond</li>
  <li><strong>Fairness:</strong> TruthfulQA [18], AgentHarm [19], TOXIGEN [20]</li>
  <li><strong>Common Sense:</strong> HellaSwag [21], SuperGLUE [22], BIG-Bench Hard</li>
  <li><strong>Multilingual Understanding:</strong> MMMLU, Belebele [7], MGSM [6]</li>
</ul>

<p>These tasks were chosen to evaluate both task-specific and general reasoning improvements, as well as the extent to which multilingual exposure reduces bias and improves robustness across domains.</p>

<h2 id="results">Results</h2>

<h3 id="optimal-split">Optimal Split</h3>

<p>As shown in Figure 1, we see that the optimal split for performance was using the 0.25 data split. This appears to retain the models initial performance and prevents catastrophic knowledge collapse.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/student-29-30/viz_output_3_2_1/by_model/summary_abs_by_model.png" alt="summary_abs_by_model" /></p>
<p><em>Fig 1. Model performance across different zh_ratio splits</em></p>

<h3 id="benchmark-performance">Benchmark Performance</h3>

<p>Overall, as shown in Figure 2, all the benchmarks evaluated seem to increase in performance, except for hellaswag. The highest relative gain we see is in humaneval with over 130% performance boost.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/student-29-30/viz_output_3_2_1/0_25/2025-06-10T18-48-50/summary_rel.png" alt="summary_rel" /></p>
<p><em>Fig 2. Relative performance gains across benchmarks</em></p>

<h4 id="detailed-benchmark-specific-performance">Detailed Benchmark Specific Performance</h4>

<p>To further understand the nuance driving these performance changes, dive into the specific subtasks for each benchmark.</p>

<p><strong>Belebele:</strong> As shown in Figure 3, 3/4 of the sub tasks are improved. With the biggest increases seen in languages like Urdu, Southern Pashto, and Lithuanian. The languages that see the largest decrease in performance are Standard Tibetan, Macedonian, and Macedonian. Surprisingly, while the training data was in Chinese, that is not where we see the biggest gain.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/student-29-30/viz_output_3_2_1/0_25/2025-06-10T18-48-50/belebele_rel.png" alt="belebele_rel" /></p>
<p><em>Fig 3. Belebele benchmark performance by language</em></p>

<p><strong>Math:</strong> For math, as shown in Figure 4, we see increase in subtopics like geometry, algebra, and probability. On the other hand, performance in prealgebra, number theory, and precalculus diminish in score.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/student-29-30/viz_output_3_2_1/0_25/2025-06-10T18-48-50/hendrycks_math_rel.png" alt="hendrycks_math_rel" /></p>
<p><em>Fig 4. Mathematics performance by subtopic</em></p>

<p><strong>MGSM:</strong> MGSM is delineated across languages. As shown in Figure 5, we see big performance gains in Chinese, Spanish, and English. On the contrary, Russian, French, and Thai.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/student-29-30/viz_output_3_2_1/0_25/2025-06-10T18-48-50/mgsm_rel.png" alt="mgsm_rel" /></p>
<p><em>Fig 5. MGSM multilingual math performance</em></p>

<p><strong>MMLU:</strong> As shown in Figure 6, logical topics like statistics, computer science, and astronomy, see big performance gains. However, public relations, machine learning, and accounting see diminishing performance.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/student-29-30/viz_output_3_2_1/0_25/2025-06-10T18-48-50/mmlu_rel.png" alt="mmlu_rel" /></p>
<p><em>Fig 6. MMLU performance across subjects</em></p>

<p><strong>TruthfulQA:</strong> As shown in Figure 7, this metric sees the most decrease in performance; with over a third of the scores decreasing. Surprisingly, we see performance decrease even in the language of interest, Chinese.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/student-29-30/viz_output_3_2_1/0_25/2025-06-10T18-48-50/truthfulqa_rel.png" alt="truthfulqa_rel" /></p>
<p><em>Fig 7. TruthfulQA performance changes</em></p>

<p>These nuanced patterns underscore the interplay between linguistic typology and task semantics. Multilingual exposure enhances certain cognitive pathways while occasionally introducing distributional biases that affect domain‑specific tasks.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>This study provides the first causal investigation into the cognitive parallels between human multilingualism and multilingual LLM pretraining. Under matched data, compute, and architectural settings, introducing moderate multilingual exposure (25% non‑English data) yields consistent gains in logical reasoning, code synthesis, and cross‑linguistic generalization, validating the cross‑lingual knowledge transfer hypothesis. These enhancements mirror cognitive benefits documented in polyglot human speakers, including flexible abstraction and resistance to knowledge erosion.</p>

<p>However, not all tasks uniformly benefit: declines in fairness benchmarks (TruthfulQA) and specific common‑sense challenges (HellaSwag) highlight potential trade‑offs. Future work should explore adaptive sampling strategies, continual pretraining techniques, and curriculum learning to maximize multilingual gains while mitigating biases. Additionally, extending analysis to larger architectures and more typologically diverse corpora will further clarify the generality of our findings.</p>

<p>By bridging cognitive science theories of multilingualism with empirical LLM evaluation, our work paves the way for designing more robust, fair, and versatile language models that harness the full spectrum of human linguistic diversity.</p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<p>[1] Perlovsky, L. (2009). Language and cognition. Neural Networks, 22(3), 247–257.</p>

<p>[2] DeKeyser, R., &amp; Koeth, J. (2011). Cognitive aptitudes for second language learning. In Handbook of research in second language teaching and learning.</p>

<p>[3] Bialystok, E., &amp; Poarch, G. (2014). Language experience changes language and cognitive ability. Zeitschrift für Erziehungswissenschaft: ZfE.</p>

<p>[4] Hurst, A., Lerer, A., Goucher, A. P., Perelman, A., Ramesh, A., Clark, A., … Radford, A. (2024). GPT-4o system card. arXiv.</p>

<p>[5] Guo, D., Yang, D., Zhang, H., Song, J., Zhang, R., Xu, R., … Bi, X. (2025). DeepSeek-R1: Incentivizing reasoning capability in LLMs via reinforcement learning. arXiv:2501.12948.</p>

<p>[6] El-Kishky, A., Chaudhary, V., Guzmán, F., &amp; Koehn, P. (2020). CCAligned: A massive collection of cross-lingual web-document pairs. In Proceedings of the EMNLP 2020.</p>

<p>[7] Lison, P., &amp; Tiedemann, J. (2016). OpenSubtitles2016: Extracting large parallel corpora from movie and TV subtitles. In Proceedings of the 10th International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2016) (pp. 923–929).</p>

<p>[8] Barrault, L., Bojar, O., Costa-jussà, M. R., Federmann, C., Fishel, M., Graham, Y., … Monz, C. (2019). Findings of the 2019 Conference on Machine Translation (WMT19). ACL.</p>

<p>[9] Schwenk, H., &amp; Douze, M. (2019). WikiMatrix: Mining 135M parallel sentences in 1620 language pairs from Wikipedia. arXiv preprint.</p>

<p>[10] Ziemski, M., Junczys-Dowmunt, M., &amp; Pouliquen, B. (2016). The United Nations Parallel Corpus v1.0. In Proceedings of the Tenth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation.</p>

<p>[11] Cobbe, K., Kosaraju, V., Bavarian, M., Chen, M., Jun, H., Kaiser, L., … Nakano, R. (2021). Training verifiers to solve math word problems. arXiv preprint arXiv:2110.14168.</p>

<p>[12] Hendrycks, D., Burns, C., Kadavath, S., Arora, A., Basart, S., Tang, D., … Steinhardt, J. (2021). Measuring mathematical problem solving with the MATH dataset. arXiv.</p>

<p>[13] Chen, M., Tworek, J., Jun, H., Yuan, Q., de Oliveira Pinto, H., Kaplan, J., … Brockman, G. (2021). Evaluating large language models trained on code. arXiv preprint arXiv:2107.03374.</p>

<p>[14] Yang, Z., Zhang, S., Thoppilan, R., … (2023). Measuring massive multitask language understanding. arXiv preprint arXiv:2307.16863.</p>

<p>[15] Lin, S., Hilton, J., &amp; Evans, O. (2021). TruthfulQA: Measuring how models mimic human falsehoods. arXiv preprint arXiv:2109.07958.</p>

<p>[16] Li, X., Xu, W., Zhang, Z., McGuffie, K., Gao, T., Henderson, P., … Chang, K.-W. (2023). AgentHarm: Evaluating harmfulness of conversational agents. arXiv preprint.</p>

<p>[17] Hartvigsen, T., Goel, S., Röttger, P., Glaese, A., &amp; Rae, J. (2022). ToxiGen: A large-scale machine-generated dataset for adversarial and implicit hate speech detection. In ACL 2022.</p>

<p>[18] Zellers, R., Holtzman, A., Bisk, Y., Farhadi, A., &amp; Choi, Y. (2019). HellaSwag: Can a machine really finish your sentence? In ACL 2019.</p>

<p>[19] Wang, A., Pruksachatkun, Y., Nangia, N., Singh, A., Michael, J., Hill, F., … Bowman, S. R. (2019). SuperGLUE: A stickier benchmark for general-purpose language understanding systems. In Proceedings of NeurIPS 2019.</p>

<p>[20] Bandarkar, L., Liang, D., Muller, B., Artetxe, M., Shukla, S. N., Husa, D., … Khabsa, M. (2024). Belebele benchmark: Parallel reading comprehension dataset in 122 language variants. ACL. URL: https://aclanthology.org/2024.acl-long.44</p>

<p>[21] Shi, F., Suzgun, M., Freitag, M., Wang, X., Srivats, S., Vosoughi, S., … Wei, J. (2022). Language models are multilingual chain-of-thought reasoners. arXiv preprint. URL: https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.03057</p>

<p>[22] ParaCrawl Project. (2024). ParaCrawl English–Chinese v1.0. Retrieved from https://web-language-models.s3.amazonaws.com/paracrawl/bonus/en-zh-v1.txt.gz</p>

<p>[23] Liu, B., Liu, X., &amp; Ji, H. (2020). ParaMed: A parallel corpus of medical research articles for Chinese-English translation. arXiv preprint arXiv:2005.09133. URL: https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.09133</p>

<p>[24] Zhang, J., Xue, B., Liu, S., &amp; Zhou, G. (2024). Web-crawled corpora for English–Chinese neural machine translation: A systematic comparison. Electronics, 13(7), 1381. https://doi.org/10.3390/electronics13071381</p>

<p>[25] Wu, J., Wei, J., &amp; Duan, W. (2021). A bilingual Chinese-English parallel corpus of financial news articles. Journal of Open Humanities Data, 7, 3. https://doi.org/10.5334/johd.62</p>

<p>[26] Zheng, Y., Zhang, R., Zhang, J., Ye, Y., Luo, Z., Feng, Z., &amp; Ma, Y. (2024). LlamaFactory: Unified efficient fine-tuning of 100+ language models. In Proceedings of the 62nd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 3: System Demonstrations) (pp. 400–410). https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2024.acl-demos.38</p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Sheriff Issaka, Salman Rahman</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Multilingual pretraining in large language models (LLMs) may confer cognitive benefits similar to those observed in multilingual humans, including enhanced reasoning and cross-linguistic generalization. Models often learn better when exposed to linguistic diversity rather than monolingual data, but the optimal balance remains unclear. In this study, we systematically investigate the impact of multilingual exposure by training LLaMA 3.2-1B models on varying ratios of English-Chinese data, characterize the performance changes across multiple benchmarks, and find that 25% multilingual exposure yields optimal results—improving logical reasoning and code synthesis by up to 130% while preventing catastrophic forgetting, though with some trade-offs in fairness metrics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Peek-A-Boo, Occlusion-Aware Visual Perception through Active Exploration</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/2024/12/13/student-01-peekaboo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Peek-A-Boo, Occlusion-Aware Visual Perception through Active Exploration" /><published>2024-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/2024/12/13/student-01-peekaboo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/2024/12/13/student-01-peekaboo.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>In this study, we present a framework for enabling
robots to locate and focus on objects that are partially or fully
occluded within their environment. We split up any robotic tasks
into two steps: Localization, where the robot searches for objects
of interest, and Task Completion, where the robot completes the
task after finding the object. We propose Peekaboo, a solution
to the Localization stage to find partially or even fully occluded
objects. We train a reinforcement learning algorithm to teach
the robot to actively reposition its camera to optimize visibility
of occluded objects. The key features include engineering a
reward function that incentivizes effective object localization and
setting up a comprehensive training environment. We develop
a simulation environment with randomness to learn to localize
from numerous initial viewpoints. Our approach also includes
the implementation of a vision encoder for processing visual
input, which allows the robot to interpret and respond to
objects and occlusions. We design metrics to quantify the model’s
performance, demonstrating its capability to handle occlusions
without any human intervention at all. The results of this work
showcase the potential for robotic systems to actively improve
their perception in cluttered or obstructed environments.</p>
</blockquote>

<!--more-->
<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#introduction" id="markdown-toc-introduction">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#prior-works" id="markdown-toc-prior-works">Prior Works</a></li>
  <li><a href="#problem-formulation" id="markdown-toc-problem-formulation">Problem Formulation</a></li>
  <li><a href="#proposed-methods-and-evaluation" id="markdown-toc-proposed-methods-and-evaluation">Proposed Methods and Evaluation</a></li>
  <li><a href="#experiments" id="markdown-toc-experiments">Experiments</a></li>
  <li><a href="#results" id="markdown-toc-results">Results</a></li>
  <li><a href="#discussion" id="markdown-toc-discussion">Discussion</a></li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion" id="markdown-toc-conclusion">Conclusion</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#future-work" id="markdown-toc-future-work">Future Work</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#links" id="markdown-toc-links">Links</a></li>
  <li><a href="#references" id="markdown-toc-references">References</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>In dynamic and cluttered environments, robotic systems
with visual perception capabilities must be able to adapt their
viewpoints to maintain visibility of target objects, even when
occlusions or obstacles obstruct their line of sight. Traditional
robotic vision systems often address this requirement by either
using a large array of static sensors, usually cameras, pointing in different orientations, or by moving a single
sensor in a predetermined path. Both approaches have their
downsides. Arrays of static sensors are far more expensive than
using a single sensor, and rely on the motion of their agent
to acquire new viewpoints. Sensors that follow predetermined
paths lack the flexibility to capture environment-dependent
information about complex scenes common in real-world
settings. These limitations serve as critical bottlenecks slowing
the advancement of vision-based robotics. Active Vision is a
promising field that aims to address these challenges. The goal
of Active Vision is to mimic the way that humans perceive
their environment: by learning to move and orient a single
sensor in ways that capture information important for completing some task.</p>

<p>Active Vision avoids the shortcomings of
the other two approaches; the agent uses a single controllable
sensor, as opposed to an array of fixed sensors to perceive
its environment, and the agent can learn to manipulate its
sensor in response to its environment in nuanced ways that
a predetermined approach could not.</p>

<p>Recent advances in reinforcement learning (RL) have looked
into enabling robots to learn behaviors directly from their
interactions with the environment, making it possible to train
autonomous systems to explore the environment, allowing
for active perception. In robotic vision tasks, RL algorithms
can enable a camera mounted on a robotic arm to not only
locate objects but also to continuously adjust its position
to avoid occlusions and improve object visibility. However,
developing such an RL framework requires overcoming several
challenges, including creating a robust training environment
that mimics the need to shift camera perspectives, and engineering reward functions that incentivize behavior promoting
consistent visibility.</p>

<p>We propose Peekaboo, an approach that addresses many
of the shortcomings of previous methods. Peekaboo’s key
insight is that the Localization and Task Completion steps in
manipulation tasks can be decoupled with minimal loss of
generality. In practice, when humans perform manipulation
tasks, we search our environment for an object before extending a hand in its direction to grasp it. The same logic applies here. Any manipulation task first requires the agent
to localize the object, along with anything else critical for
completing the task. Peekaboo focuses on this Localization
step, but unlike previous works is designed to be robust to
very heavy occlusions, and allows the camera to be controlled
with many degrees of freedom.</p>

<h2 id="prior-works">Prior Works</h2>

<p>Prior works in Active Vision address similar problems to
ours, but all differ in some key areas. While there are many
works in Active Vision, we mention those most relevant to
our method. A recent approach by researchers at Google
Deepmind proposes using navigation data to enhance the
performance of cross-embodiment manipulation tasks [8]. The
researchers demonstrate that learning a general approach to
navigation from sources using different embodiments is key
to performing manipulation tasks. Their findings reinforce the
notion that navigation is a robotics control primitive that can
aid any task, even those that do not explicitly perform navigation.</p>

<p>Other works like those by researchers from the University of Texas at Austin have proposed performing complex
tasks using an “information-seeking” and an “information-receiving” policy to guide the search task and manipulation task separately [3]. While impressive, their approach Learning
to Look is designed to perform complex manipulation tasks in
simple unobstructed environments with limited camera motion.
In contrast, our goal is to operate in environments designed to
hinder search tasks and force the agent to substantially move
its camera to succeed. There has also been plenty of work
in using Active Vision as a tool to improve performance in
well-studied tasks like grasping [6] and object classification
[7]. More recently, there has been an increased focus on
learning Active Vision policies from human demonstrations
using Imitation Learning. Ian Chuang et al. propose a method
that allows a human teleoperator to control both a camera and
a robotic arm in a VR environment in order to collect near-optimal human demonstration data of Active Vision tasks like inserting a key into a lock.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/pworksfig1.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Using learned Active Vision policies as a method to acquire novel views of objects to aid in object classification.</em></p>
</div>

<p>Two prior works stand out as particularly similar to our task
and deserve additional attention. The first approach by Stanford researchers, DREAM, proposes decoupling their agent’s
task into an explorative navigation step and exploitative task
completion stage, each of which is learned separately [5]. This
approach relies on an intrinsic task ID, and leverages memory
from previous explorative iterations through a memorization
process to aid it in the current iteration. While the researchers
demonstrate impressive results, we find that their environment
is somewhat limited. Since the researchers are performing
navigation, their agent is limited to moving in two degrees
of freedom, and rotating in a single degree of freedom. In
contrast, our approach freely manipulates the agent in six
degrees of freedom. In addition, their task is designed such
that the agent can physically access the entire environment:
an assumption that is often not true in physical systems in the
real world.</p>

<p>Another highly relevant paper from researchers
at Carnegie Mellon uses Active Vision to aid a manipulation
task in the presence of visual occlusions [1]. The authors
propose a task of pushing a target cube onto a target coordinate
using a robotic arm, where the agent learns to independently
manipulate its robotic arm and the camera from which it sees
to avoid physical occlusions preventing task completion. Like
DREAM, the proposed method limits the agent to few degrees
of freedom in its motion. In addition, the agent operates on
fairly “weak” occlusions that rarely impede task completion.
Lastly, the authors learn a single policy that jointly manipulates
the robotic arm and controls the camera – a process we
believe can be decoupled.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/pworks2.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Learning to perform manipulation in the presence of visual occlusions by learning to control the camera. The agent jointly learns to control the robotic arm to move the cube onto the target, and control the camera to avoid visual obstructions.</em></p>
</div>

<h2 id="problem-formulation">Problem Formulation</h2>

<p>We contribute a novel task formulation unique to Peekaboo,
and central to performing occlusion-aware search. We train
Peekaboo using a Reinforcement Learning framework, which
requires us to define three components: the environment, the
agent, and the reward function.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/mdp.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Markov Decision Process (MDP) Framework</em></p>
</div>

<p>The environment is a simple indoor room, containing a
central table. On the table lies a randomly positioned target
cube and a large randomly positioned wall meant to block the
view of the cube.</p>

<p>The agent is a 6-DoF Panda robotic arm, initialized to look
in a random direction. It can move its end effector in any
direction, and rotate its end effector to any orientation. The
agent observes its environment through a sensor in its hand
that captures images from the hand’s point of view.
The reward function is a binary reward function. The value
of the reward is one if the target cube is within the frame of
the robotic arm’s camera observation. Otherwise, if the cube
is off-frame, or occluded by the wall, the value of the reward
is zero. This reward function encourages the agent to search
its environment until it can see the target cube.
Using this particular task, we aim to train Peekaboo such
that it can learn to search around occlusions to locate the target
cube, regardless of variations in the scene.
In summary, we focus on building a flexible, RL-based
framework that enables a robotic arm-mounted camera to
autonomously determine the optimal perspectives for tracking
objects, particularly in environments where occlusions are
frequent. To achieve this, we will:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Introduce randomness</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Randomize both the environment and camera settings during the training phase.</li>
      <li>Ensure the model is robust to variable conditions.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Include a vision encoder</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Process incoming visual data effectively.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Incorporate a reinforcement learning (RL) algorithm</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Train the camera’s decision-making process.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Engineer a reward function</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Emphasize maintaining clear sightlines.</li>
      <li>Penalize occlusions to improve performance.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>This work contributes to the growing field of adaptive
robotic vision, offering a method for giving robots autonomous, context-aware vision capabilities that can support
applications requiring real-time adaptability in unpredictable
environments.</p>

<h2 id="proposed-methods-and-evaluation">Proposed Methods and Evaluation</h2>
<p>We propose a two stage RL training framework that allows
our robot to first search for and focus on the object of interest,
and then complete the desired task by interacting with the
object. The focus of our methods will be on training and
testing the first stage of this framework, as there are many
prior works that focus on task completion. We will refer to
this first stage as Localization and the second stage as Task
Completion. The Localization phase will consist of training
an RL agent that learns to move an egocentric, or first person
view, camera to search around occlusions by exploring the
environment, with the end goal of localizing the object of
interest in its frame of view.</p>

<p>We will approach this problem using a custom environment
in Robosuite. Our environment will be built off of the base
Lift task environment, with modifications made to create
occlusions. Specifically, we will put a wall in between the
robotic arm and the cube that the arm is trying to lift. This
will be the main occlusion that is dealt with in our Wall task.
In its initial frame observation of the environment, the robot
will not be able to see the cube it is trying to lift, as it will be
covered by the wall. We also introduced cube randomization,
camera randomization, and arm randomization. The cube and
arm randomization was done through the Robosuite framework. The camera and wall randomization relied on custom
quaternions that changed the orientation of our objects. The
goal of the overall task is for the robot to search for the cube,
find it behind the wall, and then lift it.</p>

<p>Through our two stage framework, we propose a MDP
formulation for the Localization stage. The state space
consists of the image observations from our robot. We will
have a camera attached the end effector of the robotic arm
to observe these images. The robot will not have access to
ground truth proprioceptive data. The action space consists
of modifying the perspective of the camera, which is done
through the Cartesian coordinates of moving the robotic arm.
The reward function will be as follows:</p>

\[\text{reward} = \begin{cases} 
      0 &amp; \text{if not in view} \\
      1 &amp; \text{if in view} 
   \end{cases}\]

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/fig1.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Fig 1. Visualization of our Reward Function</em>.</p>
</div>

<p>If the cube is in view, we get a reward of 1, and if it is not, the reward is 0. We will implement this in the environment using the ground truth proprioceptive data of the robotic arm, the wall, and the cube. Using this position data, we can calculate the angle in between the robotic arm and wall, and the robotic arm and the cube. These angles can then indicate if the wall is blocking the robotic arm’s frame of view from the cube or not, which allows us to return a reward of 0 or 1. Given that the robot does not have access to this ground truth data, we are essentially teaching the robot to recognize and search around occlusions when they show up prominently in its camera frame.</p>

<p>Here is a snippet from our code:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>def reward(obs):
    target_vertices, wall_vertices, camera_position, camera_vec, camera_bloom = preprocess(obs)

    # if any corner of the target cube is outside of frame, return 0
    for target_vertex in target_vertices:
        if not target_visible_in_conical_bloom(target_vertex, camera_position, camera_vec, camera_bloom):
            return 0

    # if any corner of the target cube is blocked by the wall, return 0
    for target_vertex in target_vertices:
        for wall_plane in wall_vertices:
            if line_segment_intersects_truncated_plane(target_vertex, camera_position, wall_plane):
                return 0
        
    # cube is entirely within bloom and is not obstructed
    return 1
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Once we have set up the Robosuite environment with the camera and reward function, we will train a PPO agent on the MDP formulation of the \(\textit{Localization}\) stage. The image observations will be processed by a pretrained Vision Encoder, which will be frozen during training. The output features of the Vision Encoder will be the inputs to our RL neural networks. Our evaluation will consist of visualizing rollouts and establishing a success rate for the \(\textit{Localization}\) phase. A rollout will be considered a success if the object of interest is seen completely unobstructed in the scene from the perspective of the robot. In order to test for generalization, we will randomize initial states of the robotic arm, the wall, and the cube. Sometimes, the cube will be completely in view, and sometimes it will be completely occluded. It will be up to the robot to learn and decide when it needs to search around the wall and when it has the object of interest in sight.</p>

<p>Our main contributions are the training and evaluation of this first stage. Now that we have run randomized tests, we have set up a foundation to implement the second stage of our proposed method. We can simply use the final, localized state of our first stage as the initial state for our \(\textit{Task Completion}\) stage, which will also be trained using the PPO algorithm. The goal then would be to first use the \(\textit{Localization}\) stage to find the desired object behind any occlusions, and then use the \(\textit{Task Completion}\) stage to execute the task. We can then visualize rollouts of this end to end pipeline and determine the success rate.</p>

<p>This two stage training can then be compared against a baseline of training one PPO agent for the entire task from scratch. In effect we want to show that while one agent is not able to both find the object and finish the task in one go, our two step approach is able to successfully break this down into multiple steps.</p>

<h2 id="experiments">Experiments</h2>
<p>Our experimental environment is in Robosuite. We use a custom Robosuite environment, built off their Lift Environment implementation. This environment provides a target cube object, a robotic arm, a mounted camera on the robotic arm, and a table. We customize this class by adding randomness to the initial positions and orientations of all of the above objects except the table. We also add our own wall, randomized in size, positioning, and orientation. Fig. 2 shows the top down view of our experiment setup. This figure is for visual understanding purposes only and the images from this camera are not used in our training. Fig. 3 shows the first person images from our mounted camera, randomized at each initialization. We use images from this camera to train the arm to move the camera to place the target object in frame. For our training runs, we can train models with varying degrees of randomization. Specifically, in this project, we experimented with turning camera randomization on and off. For all of our training runs, we kept wall and cube randomization always on.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/fig2.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Fig 2. Examples of Top down view of randomized initialization</em>.</p>
</div>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/fig3.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Fig 3. Examples of First person view of randomized initialization</em>.</p>
</div>

<p>For our training process, we interpret the camera image using DINOv2, a vision transformer based vision encoder, and we feed the results into our reward function. This vision encoder takes in images of size 224 by 224 from the environment and outputs 384 features to our RL policy.</p>

<p>We use a proximal policy optimization (PPO) reinforcement learning algorithm that trains our model to look at the target object. We initialize our RL policy to be a 2 layer MLP with 256 activations per layer, taking the feature inputs from our vision encoder and outputing the action for our robotic arm. We configure this model through the Stable-Baselines3 library. Ideally, we would like to train our policy for 1 million timesteps, which amounts to 2000 episodes, but due to training time constraints, we begin with 200k timesteps, which amounts to 400 episodes. Further discussion of training is presented in our results.</p>

<p>Our metrics for the model that we trained are the rewards that we defined earlier. We set the episode horizon to 500, meaning that there is a total possible reward per episode of 500. A lower reward indicates that the policy struggled to find the cube. The closer the reward is to 500 the better, indicating that our policy was able to localize the cube early in the episode, and learned to keep it within view the entire time.</p>

<h2 id="results">Results</h2>

<p>For our results, we evaluate two main training runs to demonstrate the performance of our method. As we are working with a completely custom environment and task, we are evaluating the performance of an approach to a new problem formulation.</p>

<p>Initially, we trained a model on our fully randomized environment, including randomization of the cube, wall, and camera angle. The reward graph for the training of this model is presented in Figure 4. The model is trained for 200k timesteps, which is about 400 episodes, and took approximately 10 hours to train. We can see that the general trend of the rewards is upwards, with an increase in rewards at around the 130k timesteps mark. However, the rewards are also oscillating after that point, showing variability and lack of convergence to our results.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/fig4.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Fig 4. Rewards Graph for training with randomization of wall, cube and
camera</em>.</p>
</div>

<p>We wanted to demonstrate more stability within our results, so the next model we trained was without camera randomization. The reward graph for this training run is presented in Figure 5. We see an increase in rewards earlier in this graph at 90k timesteps, but then it drops again before picking up towards the end of training. Again, we see that our rewards do not converge.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/fig5.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Fig 5. Rewards Graph for training with randomization of only wall and cube</em>.</p>
</div>

<p>In order to test if the model converges, we decided to continue training the model with full environment randomization (camera, wall, and cube) for 1 million time steps, which took 40+ hours. Unfortunately, this training run did not converge either, and showed the same up and down performance that our shorter training runs displayed. Therefore, we see that naively training the model for longer does not improve performance.</p>

<h2 id="discussion">Discussion</h2>
<p>When we tested our model after training, we saw that our policy’s actions greatly depends on the initial conditions of the task. Since we are randomizing the environment before every episode, the initial conditions could vary from episode to episode. In the case that the wall or cube are in view in the beginning, the model performs reasonably by searching around them. However, we also see many cases when the robotic arm is pointed in an arbitrary direction away from the wall and cube. In this case, it sees just a blank white image of the table. This initial observation gives the robot no information with which to find the cube or even start searching, since that image is the only observation (we do not give the robot proprioceptive data). There is no indication within the image which way it should even search, as that would change from episode to episode due to environment randomization. We believe that this variance in the task causes instability in performance, which aligns with the results we are seeing. When there is a favorable initial condition, the model learns well, but when there is no useful information in the initial condition, performance declines and causes instability in  rewards. This performance would explain why our training graphs look the way they do, and why training does not converge simply with training for longer.</p>

<p>It is also important to note that even though we trained for 10+ hours, that only amounted to 400 episodes, which is not very much compared to other environments that train RL models with training episodes in the thousands. This increase in compute goes back to our problem setup, where we settled on the computationally expensive DinoV2 vision encoder with high resolution images, and set the complexity of our task through drastic randomization of our task environment. In future works, especially with a visually simple task environment (the only objects are a wall and cube, with no visual intricacies) it may have been better to use a smaller Vision Encoder like a ResNet or train our own CNNPolicy with lower resolution images. Additionally, we had hoped that the exploration of RL would allow it to learn to overcome drastic randomization, but through our results it seems that we were potentially wrong. It may have been better to start with no randomization and just a wall occluding a cube, and once that was working, we could incrementally add randomization to increase complexity. Once these changes are implemented, we believe that our solution could be a viable solution to the active exploration problem that we are working on.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>We present Peek-A-Boo, a two stage Reinforcement Learning framework that aims to break down any task into two stages: Localization/Search and Task Completion. We create a custom task environment with occlusions and randomization, an engineered reward function, and train an RL model with a Visual Encoder to complete the Localization stage. Through our model training, we are able to demonstrate promise in our approach through generally increasing rewards despite variability in training performance.</p>

<h3 id="future-work">Future Work</h3>
<p>Future work would focus on simplifying the task with less drastic randomization to show stable performance. Then, we can scale up to more complicated tasks. Future work could also look into other ways to stabilize the performance of the model. For instance, the Localization stage of our framework could be approached using IBRL (Imitation Bootstrapped Reinforcement Learning) [4] in order to improve stability through Imitation Learning while allowing the model to also explore the environment through RL. Additionally, another avenue of future work could be automating the reward function using object detection or semantic segmentation on the observation image. We have engineering a reward function using ground truth data, but that may not always be available when applying this framework.</p>

<p>Overall, we see this as a promising first step for active perception and occlusion-aware robotics. We are excited to see the advancements in this field to hopefully one day see robot policies that are able to explore and generalize to any extenuating circumstance that they face in their environment.</p>

<h2 id="links">Links</h2>
<p><a href="https://github.com/ophirsim/Peekaboo">Link to our codebase</a></p>

<p>Custom feature extractor using the pretrained DINOv2 base model from timm: <a href="https://github.com/ophirsim/Peekaboo/blob/main/vision_encoder.py">Link</a></p>

<p>Stable Baselines Documentation: <a href="https://stable-baselines3.readthedocs.io/en/master/modules/ppo.html">Link</a></p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>[1] Cheng, R., Agarwal, A., &amp; Fragkiadaki, K.
(2018). Reinforcement Learning of Active Vision
for Manipulating Objects under Occlusions.
Conference on Robot Learning, 422-431.
http://proceedings.mlr.press/v87/cheng18a/cheng18a.pdf</p>

<p>[2] Chuang, I., Lee, A., Gao, D., &amp; Soltani, I. (2024). Active
Vision Might Be All You Need: Exploring Active Vision in Bimanual Robotic Manipulation. arXiv preprint
arXiv:2409.17435.</p>

<p>[3] Dass, S., Hu, J., Abbatematteo, B., Stone, P., &amp; Martin, R. (2024). Learning to Look: Seeking Information for Decision Making via Policy Factorization. arXiv
preprint arXiv:2410.18964.</p>

<p>[4] Hu, H., Mirchandani, S., &amp; Sadigh, D. (2024). Imitation
Bootstrapped Reinforcement Learning. arXiv [Cs.LG].
Retrieved from http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.02198</p>

<p>[5] Liu, E. Z., Finn, C., Liang, P., &amp; Raghunathan, A.
(2021, November 12). Decoupling exploration and exploitation in meta-reinforcement learning without sacrifices. Exploration in Meta-Reinforcement Learning.
https://ezliu.github.io/dream/</p>

<p>[6] Natarajan, S., Brown, G., &amp; Calli, B. (2021).
Aiding Grasp Synthesis for Novel Objects Using Heuristic-Based and Data-Driven Active Vision Methods. Frontiers in Robotics and AI, 8.
https://doi.org/10.3389/frobt.2021.696587</p>

<p>[7] Safronov, E., Piga, N., Colledanchise, M., &amp;
Natale, L. (2021, August 2). Active perception
for ambiguous objects classification. arXiv.
https://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.00737.pdf</p>

<p>[8] Yang, J., Glossop, C., Bhorkar, A., Shah, D., Vuong,
Q., Finn, C., … &amp; Levine, S. (2024). Pushing the
limits of cross-embodiment learning for manipulation
and navigation. arXiv preprint arXiv:2402.19432.</p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Medha Kini, Ophir Siman-Tov</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this study, we present a framework for enabling robots to locate and focus on objects that are partially or fully occluded within their environment. We split up any robotic tasks into two steps: Localization, where the robot searches for objects of interest, and Task Completion, where the robot completes the task after finding the object. We propose Peekaboo, a solution to the Localization stage to find partially or even fully occluded objects. We train a reinforcement learning algorithm to teach the robot to actively reposition its camera to optimize visibility of occluded objects. The key features include engineering a reward function that incentivizes effective object localization and setting up a comprehensive training environment. We develop a simulation environment with randomness to learn to localize from numerous initial viewpoints. Our approach also includes the implementation of a vision encoder for processing visual input, which allows the robot to interpret and respond to objects and occlusions. We design metrics to quantify the model’s performance, demonstrating its capability to handle occlusions without any human intervention at all. The results of this work showcase the potential for robotic systems to actively improve their perception in cluttered or obstructed environments.]]></summary></entry></feed>