<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-06-10T23:57:46-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/feed.xml</id><title type="html">2025S, UCLA CS269 Course Projects</title><subtitle>Course projects for UCLA CS269, Seminar on AI Agents and Foundation Models</subtitle><author><name>UCLAdeepvision</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Frontier of Image and Video Generation Models.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/2025/06/10/student-15-yixin-wan-img-video-gen.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Frontier of Image and Video Generation Models." /><published>2025-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/2025/06/10/student-15-yixin-wan-img-video-gen</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/2025/06/10/student-15-yixin-wan-img-video-gen.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Recent advances in deep learning have revolutionized image generation, from traditional Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs)-based models to diffusion-based and more recent black box models, to produce increasingly photorealistic visuals. These image generation advances allow for the generation of faithful, realistic, and high-resolution visual contents based on textual instructions, and have found success in domains like digital art, advertising, and prototyping. Furthermore, to achieve utility in more dynamic storytelling and immersive content creation, researchers further studied video generation for creating coherent, temporally consistent motion content directly from data. This paves the way for new applications in filmmaking, virtual reality, marketing, and beyond. However, generating videos introduces new challenges far beyond those faced in static image synthesis: models must not only render realistic frames, but also capture motion dynamics, long-range temporal dependencies, and scene coherence. Moreover, obtaining large-scale, high-quality video data for training remains a bottleneck, and quality control becomes more complex when both spatial and temporal dimensions are involved. Along similar lines, the further incorporation of audio effects with video generation has also become an emerging research field. As research pushes the boundary of what’s possible, video generation has become one of the most exciting—and demanding—frontiers in AI-driven content creation.</p>
</blockquote>

<!--more-->
<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#introduction" id="markdown-toc-introduction">Introduction</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#image-generation" id="markdown-toc-image-generation">Image Generation</a></li>
      <li><a href="#video-generation" id="markdown-toc-video-generation">Video Generation</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#prior-works-on-image-generation" id="markdown-toc-prior-works-on-image-generation">Prior Works on Image Generation</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#generative-adversarial-networks-2014-3" id="markdown-toc-generative-adversarial-networks-2014-3">Generative Adversarial Networks (2014) [3]</a></li>
      <li><a href="#high-resolution-image-synthesis-with-latent-diffusion-models-2021-4" id="markdown-toc-high-resolution-image-synthesis-with-latent-diffusion-models-2021-4">High-Resolution Image Synthesis with Latent Diffusion Models (2021) [4]</a></li>
      <li><a href="#scalable-diffusion-models-with-transformers-2022-5" id="markdown-toc-scalable-diffusion-models-with-transformers-2022-5">Scalable Diffusion Models with Transformers (2022) [5]</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#prior-works-on-video-generation" id="markdown-toc-prior-works-on-video-generation">Prior Works on Video Generation</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#video-generation-from-text-2017-6" id="markdown-toc-video-generation-from-text-2017-6">Video Generation from Text (2017) [6]</a></li>
      <li><a href="#video-diffusion-models-2022-7" id="markdown-toc-video-diffusion-models-2022-7">Video Diffusion Models (2022) [7]</a></li>
      <li><a href="#photorealistic-video-generation-with-diffusion-models-2023-8" id="markdown-toc-photorealistic-video-generation-with-diffusion-models-2023-8">Photorealistic Video Generation with Diffusion Models (2023) [8]</a></li>
      <li><a href="#googles-veo-models" id="markdown-toc-googles-veo-models">Google’s Veo Models</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#extra-credit-task-implementation-and-experiments" id="markdown-toc-extra-credit-task-implementation-and-experiments">Extra Credit Task: Implementation and Experiments</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#task-formulation" id="markdown-toc-task-formulation">Task Formulation</a></li>
      <li><a href="#evaluation" id="markdown-toc-evaluation">Evaluation</a></li>
      <li><a href="#results" id="markdown-toc-results">Results</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion" id="markdown-toc-conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
  <li><a href="#references" id="markdown-toc-references">References</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Using AI models for generating faithful, stylistic, and high-resolution multimodal visual contents has become an increasingly important research topic. Recent AI community has witnessed groundbreaking multimodal generative models such as OpenAI’s DALL-E 3 [1] and Google’s Veo-3 [2]. With the rise of a myriad of state-of-the-art approaches, this blog aims at introducing representative works in the image and video generation domain, as well as summarizing the advantages and disadvantages of these prior approaches. Additionally, we conduct scientific experiments to explore one of the crucial limitations on compositionality in image generation models.</p>

<h3 id="image-generation">Image Generation</h3>
<p>Many previous research have approached the task if image generation with different model structures. In this blog, we focus on 3 representative structures in the history of research on image generation: Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs), diffusion models with U-Net Backbones, and transformer-based diffusion models.</p>

<p><em><ins>GAN‑Based Models.</ins></em> GANs are among the earliest and most influential approaches to image generation. A typical GAN framework consist of two neural networks components: a generator and a discriminator. During training, the generator is optimized to produce synthetic data samples, whereas the discriminator is trained to distinguish the synthetic generated samples from real data. This adversarial training strategy allows the generator to gradually learn to create increasingly realistic visual outputs.</p>

<p><em><ins>Diffusion Models with U-Net Backbones.</ins></em> Diffusion models gained significant attention for their ability to generate high-quality samples with improved training stability. The diffusion process gradually stacks Gaussian noise on training data, until it becomes indistinguishable from random noise. Then, a U-Net-based neural network is then trained to reverse the noising process to denoise and reconstruct the clean data from noisy inputs step by step. At inference time, the model starts from a fully noisy input and gradually refines it into a realistic visual sample.</p>

<p><em><ins>Diffusion Models with Transformers.</ins></em> Recent research introduce Diffusion Transformers (DiTs), a new class of diffusion models based on the Transformer architecture. DiT structure replaces the previously-adopted convolutional U-Net backbone with a transformer, which operates on latent patches. This approach achieves unprecedented performance in high-quality image generation.</p>

<!-- Flow matching builds on ideas from diffusion models, while simplifying the training process and retaining strong generative capabilities at the same time. Unlike traditional diffusion models that rely on iterative denoising steps, flow matching offers a more direct framework: it trains models to predict conditional velocity fields that guide samples from noise to data in a single pass. This streamlined approach not only reduces complexity in implementation but also generalizes well across domains, making it an appealing alternative for scalable and efficient image generation. -->

<h3 id="video-generation">Video Generation</h3>
<p>Similar to image generation, we introduce 3 representative structures in video generation models: Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs), diffusion models with U-Net Backbones, and transformer-based diffusion models.</p>

<p><em><ins>GAN‑Based Models.</ins></em> Early work in video generation extended the GAN framework—originally designed for images—to the spatiotemporal domain. Models like VGAN, TGAN, and MoCoGAN employed convolutional architectures that generated short clips by jointly optimizing a frame-wise video generator and a discriminator that assesses both spatial realism and temporal coherence. These methods were groundbreaking but suffered from limitations: temporal artifacts, mode collapse, and difficulties scaling to longer durations or higher resolutions due to the adversarial training instability and limited capacity to model complex motion patterns.</p>

<p><em><ins>Diffusion Models with U-Net Backbones.</ins></em> The arrival of diffusion models brought significant improvements. Inspired by DDPMs, video diffusion models iteratively denoise frames using U‑Net architectures conditioned on neighboring frames and noise timesteps. State-of-the-art frameworks—such as those behind Imagen Video and VideoFusion—either operate in pixel space with 3D U-Nets or in latent spaces with cascaded upscaling, offering enhanced spatial fidelity and smoother temporal dynamics 
en.wikipedia.org. These models, however, remain computationally intensive, often requiring cascaded training pipelines and careful temporal alignment to retain consistency across frames.</p>

<p><em><ins>Diffusion Models with Transformers.</ins></em> More recent works explored transformer-based approaches for photorealistic video generation with diffusion models. This is usually achieved by extending ViT blocks in transformer-based image diffusion models with temporal attention layers, which adds a temporal dimension to the generated outcome and allows for the generation of consistent videos.</p>

<!-- The latest generation pivots toward flow matching, a framework that generalizes diffusion via learning continuous vector field mappings between noise and data distributions. In video generation, models like “Pyramidal Flow Matching” combine a temporal U‑Net diffusion transformer with hierarchical flow-matching stages to compress motion history and process multiple resolutions end‑to‑end. These methods have achieved, for instance, 5–10 s videos at 768p and 24 fps using fewer GPU resources by unifying denoising, temporal consistency, and resolution scaling. Complementary work in latent flow matching also exploits compact motion representations and optical-flow priors, significantly reducing computation while preserving high fidelity and seamless motion. -->
<!-- 
In summary, the progression from GAN-based methods—focused on adversarial spatial-temporal discrimination—to U‑Net-driven diffusion pipelines, and finally to unified flow-matching models, reflects a clear trajectory: GAN → Diffusion (U-Net) → Flow Matching Diffusion. Each phase addresses the challenges of temporal coherence, spatial fidelity, computational efficiency, and scalability, shaping the current landscape of video generation research. -->

<h2 id="prior-works-on-image-generation">Prior Works on Image Generation</h2>

<!-- Prior works in Active Vision address similar problems to
ours, but all differ in some key areas. While there are many
works in Active Vision, we mention those most relevant to
our method. A recent approach by researchers at Google
Deepmind proposes using navigation data to enhance the
performance of cross-embodiment manipulation tasks [8]. The
researchers demonstrate that learning a general approach to
navigation from sources using different embodiments is key
to performing manipulation tasks. Their findings reinforce the
notion that navigation is a robotics control primitive that can
aid any task, even those that do not explicitly perform navigation.  -->

<!-- Other works like those by researchers from the University of Texas at Austin have proposed performing complex
tasks using an "information-seeking" and an "information-receiving" policy to guide the search task and manipulation task separately [3]. While impressive, their approach Learning
to Look is designed to perform complex manipulation tasks in
simple unobstructed environments with limited camera motion.
In contrast, our goal is to operate in environments designed to
hinder search tasks and force the agent to substantially move
its camera to succeed. There has also been plenty of work
in using Active Vision as a tool to improve performance in
well-studied tasks like grasping [6] and object classification
[7]. More recently, there has been an increased focus on
learning Active Vision policies from human demonstrations
using Imitation Learning. Ian Chuang et al. propose a method
that allows a human teleoperator to control both a camera and
a robotic arm in a VR environment in order to collect near-optimal human demonstration data of Active Vision tasks like inserting a key into a lock. -->

<h3 id="generative-adversarial-networks-2014-3">Generative Adversarial Networks (2014) [3]</h3>
<p>Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) revolutionized AI image generation by creating realistic and high-quality images from random noise. Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) consist of two neural networks–the Generator and the Discriminator–that compete with each other. The generator creates images from random noise while the Discriminator evaluates images to classify them as real or fake which leads to continuous improvement in the quality of generated samples. The Discriminator starts by being trained on a dataset containing real images. Its goal is to differentiate between these real images and fake images generated by the Generator. Through backpropagation and gradient descent it adjusts its parameters to improve its ability to accurately classify real and generated images. In parallel, Generator is trained to produce images that are increasingly difficult for the Discriminator to distinguish from real images. Initially it generates random noise but as training progresses it learns to generate images that resemble those in the training dataset. Generator’s parameters are adjusted based on the feedback from the Discriminator helps in optimizing the Generator’s ability to create more realistic and high-quality images.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-yixin-wan/img_5.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Example of the training pipeline of using GANs to generate images of facees. The generator learns to create realistic depictions that are as indistinguishable from real images as possible, as judged by the discriminator.</em></p>
</div>

<ul>
  <li>Advantages:
    <ul>
      <li>Earliest attempts to produce high-quality and realistic images.</li>
      <li>Allowing flexible applications like style transfer and super resolution.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Disadvantages:
    <ul>
      <li>Model Collapse. The generator creates limited or repetitive outputs, failing to capture the variety of the training data.</li>
      <li>Training Instability. The training process could become unstable, causing the generator and discriminator to diverge or fluctuate instead of improving together.</li>
      <li>Hyperparameter Sensitivity: Model performance is very sensitive to choices of hyperparameters like learning rate and optimizer settings. This requires careful tuning at the risk of model collapse during training.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="high-resolution-image-synthesis-with-latent-diffusion-models-2021-4">High-Resolution Image Synthesis with Latent Diffusion Models (2021) [4]</h3>
<p>The first generation of diffusion-based models, which usually adopt a U-Net-based structure, offer an efficient and scalable approach to generative modeling by operating in a compressed latent space rather than pixel space. This design dramatically reduces the computational cost of high-resolution image synthesis while preserving visual fidelity. The model uses a U-Net architecture as the denoiser within a diffusion process, enabling it to iteratively refine noisy latent representations into coherent image features. By combining the strengths of autoencoding for dimensionality reduction and diffusion for high-quality generation, latent diffusion models achieve state-of-the-art performance in generating detailed and diverse images across various conditioning tasks.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-yixin-wan/img_6.png" style="width: 600px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Example of how to condition Latent Diffusion Models (LDMs) for text-to-image generation, either via concatenation or by a more general cross-attention mechanism.</em></p>
</div>

<ul>
  <li>Advantages:
    <ul>
      <li>The generation of high-resolution image samples.</li>
      <li>More stable training process and less model collapse than GAN-based approach.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Disadvantages:
    <ul>
      <li>Context Dependency: U-Net-based diffusion models often struggle with capturing long-range dependencies and global context in the input data. This is due to the limited receptive field of convolutional layers.</li>
      <li>Position / Spatial Control: Convolution in U-Nets are translation invariant, trating features as the same regardless of their positions in the image. Therefore, positional and spatial control in generated images are more difficult to achieve.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="scalable-diffusion-models-with-transformers-2022-5">Scalable Diffusion Models with Transformers (2022) [5]</h3>
<!-- Flow Matching (FM) is a recent and increasingly influential paradigm in generative modeling that has gained significant traction within the deep probabilistic machine learning community. Positioned at the intersection of Continuous Normalizing Flows (CNFs) and Diffusion Models (DMs), flow matching seeks to unify the strengths of both approaches while addressing their respective limitations—such as the computational inefficiency of CNFs and the slow sampling process of traditional diffusion models. At its core, flow matching involves learning velocity fields that guide samples from noise to data in a single, continuous transformation, enabling more efficient and scalable generation. In this blog post, we’ll explore the foundational concepts of flow matching, its distinctive advantages, and how it is reshaping the landscape of generative modeling. -->
<p>Transformer-based diffusion models, known as Diffusion Transformers (DiTs), are inspired by the Vision Transformer (ViT) and replace the traditional U-Net backbone in latent diffusion models with a transformer architecture. While being largely similar to standard ViTs, DiTs make key modifications to the structure to effectively handle conditional inputs, like diffusion timesteps, for diffusion-based generation. In their paper ‘Scalable Diffusion Models with Transformers’, the authors discovered that the most effective design leverages adaptive layer normalization (adaLN). adaLN modulates the activations prior to residual connections, and is initialized to behave like an identity function at the beginning of the training process. This simple yet impactful change significantly improves the quality of model-generated outputs as measured by FID scores, showing transformers as a flexible alternative to U-Nets in diffusion-based image synthesis.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-yixin-wan/img_7.png" style="width: 600px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>The Diffusion Transformer (DiT) architecture. Left: Conditional latent DiT models. The input latent is decomposed into patches and processed by several DiT blocks. Right: Details of the DiT blocks. After experimenting with variants of standard transformer blocks that incorporate conditioning via adaptive layer norm, cross-attention and extra input tokens, adaptive layer norm is empirically proved to work best.</em></p>
</div>

<ul>
  <li>Advantages:
    <ul>
      <li>Better handle long range dependencies in contexts compared to U-Net-based approaches.</li>
      <li>Better control positional and spatial control of generated subjects through positional encodings.</li>
      <li>Better efficiency at inference time.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Disadvantages:
    <ul>
      <li>Still not the best with positional and spatial control.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<!-- ### Summary of Previous Works
Previously -->
<!-- 
### Challenges and Limitations -->

<h2 id="prior-works-on-video-generation">Prior Works on Video Generation</h2>

<h3 id="video-generation-from-text-2017-6">Video Generation from Text (2017) [6]</h3>
<p>One of the earlier efforts in text-to-video synthesis is the 2017 work titled Video Generation from Text, which introduced a conditional generative model designed to capture both static and dynamic aspects of video content from textual input. The proposed hybrid framework combines a Variational Autoencoder (VAE) with a Generative Adversarial Network (GAN), enabling the model to learn nuanced video representations. In this architecture, static features—referred to as the “gist”—are extracted from the text and used to generate coarse layouts such as background colors and object placements.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-yixin-wan/img_1.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Samples of video generation from text. Universal background information (the gist) is produced based on the text. The text-to-filter step generates the action (e.g., “play golf”). The red circle shows the center of motion in the generated video.</em></p>
</div>

<p>Meanwhile, dynamic features are handled by converting the text into an image filter that modulates the temporal evolution of the scene. To train and evaluate the model, the authors constructed a dataset of short video clips collected from YouTube, tailored to align visual content with descriptive captions. This work laid early groundwork for bridging language and temporally consistent visual generation.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-yixin-wan/img_2.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Framework of the proposed text-to-video generation method. The gist generator is in the green box. The encoded
text is concatenated with the encoded frame to form the joint hidden representation zd, which further transformed into zg. The
video generator is in the yellow box. The text description is transformed into a filter kernel (Text2Filter) and applied to the gist.
The generation uses the features zg with injected random noise. Following this point, the flow chart forms a standard GAN
framework with a final discriminator to judge whether a video and text pair is real or synthetic. After training, the CNN image
encoder is ignored.</em></p>
</div>

<ul>
  <li>Advantages:
    <ul>
      <li>Earliest attempts to extend image generation in the temporal dimension with promising results.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Disadvantages:
    <ul>
      <li>Struggled to maintain temporal consistency and realistic motion across frames.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="video-diffusion-models-2022-7">Video Diffusion Models (2022) [7]</h3>
<p>The 2022 paper Video Diffusion Models marked a pivotal moment in generative modeling by demonstrating the first successful application of diffusion models to video generation, covering both unconditional and conditional settings. The core architecture employs a 3D space-time U-Net, which directly models the joint spatial and temporal structure of fixed-length video clips. A notable innovation in this work is the use of factorized U-Nets, which not only allow the model to scale to variable sequence lengths but also enable joint training on both video and image data—an approach shown to significantly improve sampling quality. To extend generation beyond fixed durations, the authors propose an autoregressive sampling scheme that conditions on previously generated segments, allowing for the synthesis of longer, coherent video sequences. The model was trained and evaluated on the UCF101 dataset, a benchmark collection of user-uploaded videos depicting 101 different human action categories. This work established diffusion models as a powerful alternative to GAN-based approaches for temporally consistent and high-fidelity video generation. They provide a public demonstration <a href="https://video-diffusion.github.io/">here</a>.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-yixin-wan/img_3.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>The 3D U-Net architecture for x<sup>^</sup><sub>θ</sub> in the diffusion model. Each block represents a 4D
tensor with axes labeled as frames × height × width × channels, processed in a space-time factorized
manner as described in Section 3. The input is a noisy video z<sub>t</sub>, conditioning c, and the log SNR λ<sub>t</sub>.
The downsampling/upsampling blocks adjust the spatial input resolution height × width by a factor
of 2 through each of the K blocks. The channel counts are specified using channel multipliers M<sub>1</sub>,
M<sub>2</sub>, ..., M<sub>K</sub>, and the upsampling pass has concatenation skip connections to the downsampling pass.</em></p>
</div>

<ul>
  <li>Advantages:
    <ul>
      <li>Improve fidelity and consistency of generated videos.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Disadvantages:
    <ul>
      <li>Short duration of generated videos (usually a couple seconds).</li>
      <li>Low resolution of generated videos.</li>
      <li>Temporal incoherence. Generated videos often suffer from flickering artifacts, inconsistent object appearances, or morphing structures that undermine realism.</li>
      <li>Unrealistic motion. Characters or objects exhibit physically implausible behavior and lacking an intuitive grasp of cause-and-effect relationships in dynamic scenes.</li>
      <li>Limited understanding of prompts, especially when tasked with generating nuanced actions, complex interactions, or scenes involving multiple entities.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="photorealistic-video-generation-with-diffusion-models-2023-8">Photorealistic Video Generation with Diffusion Models (2023) [8]</h3>
<p>The December 2023 paper Photorealistic Video Generation with Diffusion Models introduced a transformer-based architecture, Window Attention Latent Transformer (W.A.L.T.), designed to advance photorealistic video synthesis through diffusion modeling. At the heart of the approach is a causal encoder that compresses both images and videos into a shared latent space, allowing unified training across modalities and facilitating seamless transition between image and video generation tasks. To address the computational challenges of high-dimensional video data, the model incorporates a specialized window attention mechanism that efficiently captures both spatial and temporal dependencies. The full system is implemented as a cascaded framework for text-to-video generation, consisting of a base latent video diffusion model followed by two successive video super-resolution diffusion stages. This multi-stage design allows the model to progressively refine outputs to high visual fidelity. The training data includes a diverse set of text-image and text-video pairs sourced from the internet and proprietary datasets, enabling the model to generalize across a wide range of visual concepts and motion patterns.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-yixin-wan/img_4.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>W.A.L.T. We encode images and videos into a shared latent space. The transformer backbone processes these latents with blocks
having two layers of window-restricted attention: spatial layers capture spatial relations in both images and video, while spatiotemporal
layers model temporal dynamics in videos and passthrough images via identity attention mask. Text conditioning is done via spatial
cross-attention.</em></p>
</div>

<ul>
  <li>Advantages:
    <ul>
      <li>Higher resolution of generated videos.</li>
      <li>Better ability to capture long-range dependencies in temporal dimension.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Disadvantages:
    <ul>
      <li>Still struggles with unrealistic motion and prompt understanding.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="googles-veo-models">Google’s Veo Models</h3>
<!-- ### Initial Release -->
<p>Google’s Veo models marks a significant advancement in video generation. However, due to their black-box nature, we are not able to analyze their model structure. Here, we discuss the capabilities of Veo models as introduced by their release blog post.</p>

<h4 id="veo-2">Veo-2</h4>
<!-- In their initial release of Veo-2, the model is able to:
* Follow both simple and complex instructions.
* Simulate real-world physics.
* Depict a wide range of visual styles.
* Produce high-quality video generation from both text and image prompts. -->
<p>In its initial release, Veo-2 demonstrates the ability to follow both simple and complex instructions, effectively interpreting nuanced prompts involving detailed actions, multi-entity interactions, and scene composition. The model also shows a stronger grasp of real-world physics, producing motion that respects physical plausibility—such as natural object trajectories, weight shifts, and environmental responses. Additionally, Veo-2 can render a diverse range of visual styles, offering greater creative flexibility. It also supports video generation from both text and image prompts, enabling users to specify scenes through rich textual descriptions or visual references.</p>

<!-- ### New Release -->
<p>The latest release of Veo-2 introduces a suite of powerful new capabilities: for instance, reference-powered video generation allows users to guide the model using images of scenes, characters, styles, or objects—akin to in-context learning for visuals. This allows for better temporal and visual consistency across frames. Advanced camera controls enable users to specify cinematic movements between angles. Seamless transitions between provided start and end frames are also enabled, producing temporally smooth videos that reflect coherent narrative arcs. Additionally, the new generation of Veo-2 supports both outpainting—extending content beyond the original frame—and inpainting, allowing for the insertion or removal of objects from existing videos, paralleling image editing capabilities in the video domain. For dynamic content, Veo-2 offers character movement control through reference videos and a tool where users can select specific objects and define their movement paths.</p>

<h4 id="veo-3">Veo-3</h4>
<!-- ### Google's new Veo-3 Model -->
<p>Google’s new Veo-3 model further elevates the realism, controllability, and quality of video generation. Veo-3 introduces the native generation of synchronized audio, allowing users to specify ambient sounds—such as birdsong or rustling leaves—directly within the prompt. In terms of physics and realism, Veo-3 achieves more lifelike motion for people, animals, and objects, exhibiting a deeper understanding of how entities interact with their environments in ways that adhere to physical laws. Additionally, Veo-3 demonstrates an enhanced comprehension of textual prompts, accurately translating subtle emotional cues, narrative tones, and complex instructions into coherent visual and auditory outputs.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Advantages:
    <ul>
      <li>State-of-the-art performance in generating high-quality, natural, and coherent videos.</li>
      <li>More realistic movements following real-world physics laws.</li>
      <li>Earliest attempt to simultaniously generate video and corresponding audio.</li>
      <li>Allow for precise prompt control of objects, motions, and audios in model generations.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Disadvantages:
    <ul>
      <li>Still struggle a little with naturalistic transitions between scenes in generated videos.</li>
      <li>Room for improvement with audio generation and incorporated in generated videos.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<!-- ### Summary of Previous Works
Early attempts at video generation primarily focused on adapting GAN architectures to the spatiotemporal domain, which, while promising, often struggled to maintain temporal consistency and realistic motion across frames. As the field progressed, the emergence of transformer-based models introduced the ability to capture long-range dependencies, a crucial factor for modeling coherent motion and scene evolution over time. Simultaneously, diffusion models—originally successful in high-quality image synthesis—were extended to video, leading to significant improvements in both fidelity and consistency. This evolution reflects an ongoing journey toward generating videos that are not only visually realistic but also temporally coherent and semantically controllable, marking a substantial leap forward in AI-driven content creation.

### Challenges and Limitations
Despite significant progress, video generation models—both early and recent—continue to face several persistent challenges. One of the most critical issues is temporal incoherence, where generated videos often suffer from flickering artifacts, inconsistent object appearances, or morphing structures that undermine realism. Models also frequently produce unrealistic motion, with characters or objects exhibiting physically implausible behavior and lacking an intuitive grasp of cause-and-effect relationships in dynamic scenes. Furthermore, many models demonstrate a limited understanding of prompts, especially when tasked with generating nuanced actions, complex interactions, or scenes involving multiple entities. These limitations highlight the difficulty of aligning spatial fidelity, temporal consistency, and semantic accuracy in a unified generative framework.

These challenges are further compounded by the short duration of generated videos, which are typically limited to just a few seconds. This constraint arises from both the high computational cost of modeling long sequences and the tendency for quality to degrade over time due to error accumulation. Additionally, many generated videos exhibit low resolution and visible artifacts, such as blurring, ghosting, or distorted textures, which diminish their realism and limit their applicability in professional settings. Another major limitation is the lack of fine-grained control over outputs—most models offer limited flexibility in specifying elements such as camera trajectories, stylistic choices, or the precise appearance and actions of objects within a scene. Finally, the high computational demands of training and inference—especially for large-scale diffusion or transformer-based models—remain a significant barrier to accessibility and widespread deployment. Together, these issues highlight the technical complexity and resource intensity of pushing video generation models toward truly robust, controllable, and scalable solutions. -->

<!-- 
## Discussion -->

<h2 id="extra-credit-task-implementation-and-experiments">Extra Credit Task: Implementation and Experiments</h2>
<p>Due to computational costs, we are not able to run experiments on video generation models. However, we implement multiple state-of-the-art image generation models and explore one of their shared limitations: positional, numerical, and spatial control of generated subjects in <em><ins>compositional image generation</ins></em>.</p>

<h3 id="task-formulation">Task Formulation</h3>
<p>Compositional Text-to-Image (T2I) generation tests models’ abilities to accurately and coherently depict multiple concepts in a unified scene based on textual instructions. We experiment with 900 detailed image generation prompts involving multiple objects, 3D-spatial relationships, and precise attributes such as color and texture. We manually define 5
distinct 3D-spatial configurations, escalating in both numerical and spatial complexity: 1 row × 2 subjects, 1 row × 3 subjects, 2 rows × 1 subject, 2 rows × 2 subjects, and 2 rows × 3 subjects. We phrase these positional configurations into natural prompt templates for further combination with generation subjects. For instance, for the configuration with 1 row and 2 subjects, the corresponding prompt template is:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“An image with 2 objects: a {(optional) attribute A} {subject A} on the left, and a {(optional) attribute B} {subject B} on the right.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="evaluation">Evaluation</h3>
<p>Our evaluation framework consists of 3 steps:</p>
<ol>
  <li>An Atomic Question Decomposition step to divide complex compositional prompts into individual questions that can be judged with binary answers (i.e. “yes” or “no”).</li>
  <li>An Atomic MLLM Feedback step that uses a strong MLLM to judge the depiction accuracy of each decomposed aspect in generated images.</li>
  <li>An Aggregated Compositional Accuracy metric that yields an objective and interpretable quantitative evaluation score for each model generation. We measure the binary feedback for each subquestion and report the proportion of correctly-depicted entities as the Aggregated Compositional Accuracy (ACA) metric.</li>
</ol>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-yixin-wan/img_8.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Evaluation Framework. Each compositional prompt is first divided into atomic questions, then answered by a MLLM feedback model, finally aggregated to be an accuracy score.</em></p>
</div>

<h3 id="results">Results</h3>
<p>Experiment results show that open-source diffusion models with U-Net structures, such as SD1.5 and SD2, exhibit limited compositional accuracy (below 50%). Performance improves with model scale, generation, and architecture improvements. For instance, SD3 and SD3.5, which utilize a transformer-based structure to replace U-Nets, both achieve remarkably higher ACA scores than the previous two, reaching above 75%. Among closed-source models, OpenAI’s gpt-image-1-high model leads with 93.51%, outperforming DALL-E 3 and Gemini. While results show promising advances in architectural and training pipelines for T2I models, we also observe a remarkable performance gap between open-sourced and closed-source models.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-yixin-wan/img_9.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Comprehensive evaluation results across 9 open- and closed-source T2I models. Closed-source commercial models achieve remarkably stronger compositional accuracy, with OpenAI’s gpt-image-1-high as the leading model.</em></p>
</div>

<p>Additionally, qualitative results show that compare to previous evaluation frameworks like T2I-CompBench++, our evaluation setting is more challenging for even strong T2I models, resulting in more failure cases.</p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-yixin-wan/img_10.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Example showing that while T2I models are capable of depicting simple compositional settings in a previous benchmark, they fall short in correctly generating images that accurately conform to complex compositional instructions in our challenging benchmark.</em></p>
</div>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>In this blog post, we introduce representative research works in the domain of image and video generation. By analyzing their advantages and disadvantages, we provide a clear overview of what has been done and what can be done in future works in these research directions. Furthermore, we conduct an in-depth analysis of one of the crucial limitations in image generation models: compositional T2I generation. By analyzing 9 state-of-the-art image generation models on our prompts, we discover the persisting pitfalls even for strong T2I models.</p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>[1] OpenAI. Dall·e 3 system card, Oct 2023. URL https://openai.com/research/
dall-e-3-system-card.</p>

<p>[2] Google DeepMind. Veo, May 2025. URL https://deepmind.google/models/veo/.</p>

<p>[3] I. J. Goodfellow, J. Pouget-Abadie, M. Mirza, B. Xu, D. Warde-Farley, S. Ozair, A. Courville, and Y. Bengio, “Generative
adversarial networks,” 2014</p>

<p>[4] R. Rombach, A. Blattmann, D. Lorenz, P. Esser, and B. Ommer. High-resolution image synthesis
with latent diffusion models. In Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision
and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), pages 10684–10695, June 2022.</p>

<p>[5] W. Peebles and S. Xie. Scalable diffusion models with transformers. In Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF
International Conference on Computer Vision, pages 4195–4205, 2023. 2, 4, 6, 7, 8</p>

<p>[6] Yitong Li, Martin Min, Dinghan Shen, David Carlson, and Lawrence Carin. 2018. Video generation from text. In Proceedings of the AAAI conference
on artificial intelligence, Vol. 32.</p>

<p>[7]  Jonathan Ho, Tim Salimans, Alexey Gritsenko, William
Chan, Mohammad Norouzi, and David J. Fleet. Video diffusion models. arXiv preprint arXiv:2204.03458, 2022. 2,
15</p>

<p>[8] A. Gupta, L. Yu, K. Sohn, X. Gu, M. Hahn, L. Fei-Fei, I. Essa, L. Jiang, and J. Lezama, “Photorealistic
video generation with diffusion models,” arXiv preprint arXiv:2312.06662, 2023.
—</p>]]></content><author><name>Yixin Wan</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recent advances in deep learning have revolutionized image generation, from traditional Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs)-based models to diffusion-based and more recent black box models, to produce increasingly photorealistic visuals. These image generation advances allow for the generation of faithful, realistic, and high-resolution visual contents based on textual instructions, and have found success in domains like digital art, advertising, and prototyping. Furthermore, to achieve utility in more dynamic storytelling and immersive content creation, researchers further studied video generation for creating coherent, temporally consistent motion content directly from data. This paves the way for new applications in filmmaking, virtual reality, marketing, and beyond. However, generating videos introduces new challenges far beyond those faced in static image synthesis: models must not only render realistic frames, but also capture motion dynamics, long-range temporal dependencies, and scene coherence. Moreover, obtaining large-scale, high-quality video data for training remains a bottleneck, and quality control becomes more complex when both spatial and temporal dimensions are involved. Along similar lines, the further incorporation of audio effects with video generation has also become an emerging research field. As research pushes the boundary of what’s possible, video generation has become one of the most exciting—and demanding—frontiers in AI-driven content creation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Peek-A-Boo, Occlusion-Aware Visual Perception through Active Exploration</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/2024/12/13/student-01-peekaboo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Peek-A-Boo, Occlusion-Aware Visual Perception through Active Exploration" /><published>2024-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/2024/12/13/student-01-peekaboo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/2024/12/13/student-01-peekaboo.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>In this study, we present a framework for enabling
robots to locate and focus on objects that are partially or fully
occluded within their environment. We split up any robotic tasks
into two steps: Localization, where the robot searches for objects
of interest, and Task Completion, where the robot completes the
task after finding the object. We propose Peekaboo, a solution
to the Localization stage to find partially or even fully occluded
objects. We train a reinforcement learning algorithm to teach
the robot to actively reposition its camera to optimize visibility
of occluded objects. The key features include engineering a
reward function that incentivizes effective object localization and
setting up a comprehensive training environment. We develop
a simulation environment with randomness to learn to localize
from numerous initial viewpoints. Our approach also includes
the implementation of a vision encoder for processing visual
input, which allows the robot to interpret and respond to
objects and occlusions. We design metrics to quantify the model’s
performance, demonstrating its capability to handle occlusions
without any human intervention at all. The results of this work
showcase the potential for robotic systems to actively improve
their perception in cluttered or obstructed environments.</p>
</blockquote>

<!--more-->
<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#introduction" id="markdown-toc-introduction">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#prior-works" id="markdown-toc-prior-works">Prior Works</a></li>
  <li><a href="#problem-formulation" id="markdown-toc-problem-formulation">Problem Formulation</a></li>
  <li><a href="#proposed-methods-and-evaluation" id="markdown-toc-proposed-methods-and-evaluation">Proposed Methods and Evaluation</a></li>
  <li><a href="#experiments" id="markdown-toc-experiments">Experiments</a></li>
  <li><a href="#results" id="markdown-toc-results">Results</a></li>
  <li><a href="#discussion" id="markdown-toc-discussion">Discussion</a></li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion" id="markdown-toc-conclusion">Conclusion</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#future-work" id="markdown-toc-future-work">Future Work</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#links" id="markdown-toc-links">Links</a></li>
  <li><a href="#references" id="markdown-toc-references">References</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>In dynamic and cluttered environments, robotic systems
with visual perception capabilities must be able to adapt their
viewpoints to maintain visibility of target objects, even when
occlusions or obstacles obstruct their line of sight. Traditional
robotic vision systems often address this requirement by either
using a large array of static sensors, usually cameras, pointing in different orientations, or by moving a single
sensor in a predetermined path. Both approaches have their
downsides. Arrays of static sensors are far more expensive than
using a single sensor, and rely on the motion of their agent
to acquire new viewpoints. Sensors that follow predetermined
paths lack the flexibility to capture environment-dependent
information about complex scenes common in real-world
settings. These limitations serve as critical bottlenecks slowing
the advancement of vision-based robotics. Active Vision is a
promising field that aims to address these challenges. The goal
of Active Vision is to mimic the way that humans perceive
their environment: by learning to move and orient a single
sensor in ways that capture information important for completing some task.</p>

<p>Active Vision avoids the shortcomings of
the other two approaches; the agent uses a single controllable
sensor, as opposed to an array of fixed sensors to perceive
its environment, and the agent can learn to manipulate its
sensor in response to its environment in nuanced ways that
a predetermined approach could not.</p>

<p>Recent advances in reinforcement learning (RL) have looked
into enabling robots to learn behaviors directly from their
interactions with the environment, making it possible to train
autonomous systems to explore the environment, allowing
for active perception. In robotic vision tasks, RL algorithms
can enable a camera mounted on a robotic arm to not only
locate objects but also to continuously adjust its position
to avoid occlusions and improve object visibility. However,
developing such an RL framework requires overcoming several
challenges, including creating a robust training environment
that mimics the need to shift camera perspectives, and engineering reward functions that incentivize behavior promoting
consistent visibility.</p>

<p>We propose Peekaboo, an approach that addresses many
of the shortcomings of previous methods. Peekaboo’s key
insight is that the Localization and Task Completion steps in
manipulation tasks can be decoupled with minimal loss of
generality. In practice, when humans perform manipulation
tasks, we search our environment for an object before extending a hand in its direction to grasp it. The same logic applies here. Any manipulation task first requires the agent
to localize the object, along with anything else critical for
completing the task. Peekaboo focuses on this Localization
step, but unlike previous works is designed to be robust to
very heavy occlusions, and allows the camera to be controlled
with many degrees of freedom.</p>

<h2 id="prior-works">Prior Works</h2>

<p>Prior works in Active Vision address similar problems to
ours, but all differ in some key areas. While there are many
works in Active Vision, we mention those most relevant to
our method. A recent approach by researchers at Google
Deepmind proposes using navigation data to enhance the
performance of cross-embodiment manipulation tasks [8]. The
researchers demonstrate that learning a general approach to
navigation from sources using different embodiments is key
to performing manipulation tasks. Their findings reinforce the
notion that navigation is a robotics control primitive that can
aid any task, even those that do not explicitly perform navigation.</p>

<p>Other works like those by researchers from the University of Texas at Austin have proposed performing complex
tasks using an “information-seeking” and an “information-receiving” policy to guide the search task and manipulation task separately [3]. While impressive, their approach Learning
to Look is designed to perform complex manipulation tasks in
simple unobstructed environments with limited camera motion.
In contrast, our goal is to operate in environments designed to
hinder search tasks and force the agent to substantially move
its camera to succeed. There has also been plenty of work
in using Active Vision as a tool to improve performance in
well-studied tasks like grasping [6] and object classification
[7]. More recently, there has been an increased focus on
learning Active Vision policies from human demonstrations
using Imitation Learning. Ian Chuang et al. propose a method
that allows a human teleoperator to control both a camera and
a robotic arm in a VR environment in order to collect near-optimal human demonstration data of Active Vision tasks like inserting a key into a lock.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/pworksfig1.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Using learned Active Vision policies as a method to acquire novel views of objects to aid in object classification.</em></p>
</div>

<p>Two prior works stand out as particularly similar to our task
and deserve additional attention. The first approach by Stanford researchers, DREAM, proposes decoupling their agent’s
task into an explorative navigation step and exploitative task
completion stage, each of which is learned separately [5]. This
approach relies on an intrinsic task ID, and leverages memory
from previous explorative iterations through a memorization
process to aid it in the current iteration. While the researchers
demonstrate impressive results, we find that their environment
is somewhat limited. Since the researchers are performing
navigation, their agent is limited to moving in two degrees
of freedom, and rotating in a single degree of freedom. In
contrast, our approach freely manipulates the agent in six
degrees of freedom. In addition, their task is designed such
that the agent can physically access the entire environment:
an assumption that is often not true in physical systems in the
real world.</p>

<p>Another highly relevant paper from researchers
at Carnegie Mellon uses Active Vision to aid a manipulation
task in the presence of visual occlusions [1]. The authors
propose a task of pushing a target cube onto a target coordinate
using a robotic arm, where the agent learns to independently
manipulate its robotic arm and the camera from which it sees
to avoid physical occlusions preventing task completion. Like
DREAM, the proposed method limits the agent to few degrees
of freedom in its motion. In addition, the agent operates on
fairly “weak” occlusions that rarely impede task completion.
Lastly, the authors learn a single policy that jointly manipulates
the robotic arm and controls the camera – a process we
believe can be decoupled.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/pworks2.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Learning to perform manipulation in the presence of visual occlusions by learning to control the camera. The agent jointly learns to control the robotic arm to move the cube onto the target, and control the camera to avoid visual obstructions.</em></p>
</div>

<h2 id="problem-formulation">Problem Formulation</h2>

<p>We contribute a novel task formulation unique to Peekaboo,
and central to performing occlusion-aware search. We train
Peekaboo using a Reinforcement Learning framework, which
requires us to define three components: the environment, the
agent, and the reward function.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/mdp.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Markov Decision Process (MDP) Framework</em></p>
</div>

<p>The environment is a simple indoor room, containing a
central table. On the table lies a randomly positioned target
cube and a large randomly positioned wall meant to block the
view of the cube.</p>

<p>The agent is a 6-DoF Panda robotic arm, initialized to look
in a random direction. It can move its end effector in any
direction, and rotate its end effector to any orientation. The
agent observes its environment through a sensor in its hand
that captures images from the hand’s point of view.
The reward function is a binary reward function. The value
of the reward is one if the target cube is within the frame of
the robotic arm’s camera observation. Otherwise, if the cube
is off-frame, or occluded by the wall, the value of the reward
is zero. This reward function encourages the agent to search
its environment until it can see the target cube.
Using this particular task, we aim to train Peekaboo such
that it can learn to search around occlusions to locate the target
cube, regardless of variations in the scene.
In summary, we focus on building a flexible, RL-based
framework that enables a robotic arm-mounted camera to
autonomously determine the optimal perspectives for tracking
objects, particularly in environments where occlusions are
frequent. To achieve this, we will:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Introduce randomness</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Randomize both the environment and camera settings during the training phase.</li>
      <li>Ensure the model is robust to variable conditions.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Include a vision encoder</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Process incoming visual data effectively.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Incorporate a reinforcement learning (RL) algorithm</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Train the camera’s decision-making process.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Engineer a reward function</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Emphasize maintaining clear sightlines.</li>
      <li>Penalize occlusions to improve performance.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>This work contributes to the growing field of adaptive
robotic vision, offering a method for giving robots autonomous, context-aware vision capabilities that can support
applications requiring real-time adaptability in unpredictable
environments.</p>

<h2 id="proposed-methods-and-evaluation">Proposed Methods and Evaluation</h2>
<p>We propose a two stage RL training framework that allows
our robot to first search for and focus on the object of interest,
and then complete the desired task by interacting with the
object. The focus of our methods will be on training and
testing the first stage of this framework, as there are many
prior works that focus on task completion. We will refer to
this first stage as Localization and the second stage as Task
Completion. The Localization phase will consist of training
an RL agent that learns to move an egocentric, or first person
view, camera to search around occlusions by exploring the
environment, with the end goal of localizing the object of
interest in its frame of view.</p>

<p>We will approach this problem using a custom environment
in Robosuite. Our environment will be built off of the base
Lift task environment, with modifications made to create
occlusions. Specifically, we will put a wall in between the
robotic arm and the cube that the arm is trying to lift. This
will be the main occlusion that is dealt with in our Wall task.
In its initial frame observation of the environment, the robot
will not be able to see the cube it is trying to lift, as it will be
covered by the wall. We also introduced cube randomization,
camera randomization, and arm randomization. The cube and
arm randomization was done through the Robosuite framework. The camera and wall randomization relied on custom
quaternions that changed the orientation of our objects. The
goal of the overall task is for the robot to search for the cube,
find it behind the wall, and then lift it.</p>

<p>Through our two stage framework, we propose a MDP
formulation for the Localization stage. The state space
consists of the image observations from our robot. We will
have a camera attached the end effector of the robotic arm
to observe these images. The robot will not have access to
ground truth proprioceptive data. The action space consists
of modifying the perspective of the camera, which is done
through the Cartesian coordinates of moving the robotic arm.
The reward function will be as follows:</p>

\[\text{reward} = \begin{cases} 
      0 &amp; \text{if not in view} \\
      1 &amp; \text{if in view} 
   \end{cases}\]

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/fig1.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Fig 1. Visualization of our Reward Function</em>.</p>
</div>

<p>If the cube is in view, we get a reward of 1, and if it is not, the reward is 0. We will implement this in the environment using the ground truth proprioceptive data of the robotic arm, the wall, and the cube. Using this position data, we can calculate the angle in between the robotic arm and wall, and the robotic arm and the cube. These angles can then indicate if the wall is blocking the robotic arm’s frame of view from the cube or not, which allows us to return a reward of 0 or 1. Given that the robot does not have access to this ground truth data, we are essentially teaching the robot to recognize and search around occlusions when they show up prominently in its camera frame.</p>

<p>Here is a snippet from our code:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>def reward(obs):
    target_vertices, wall_vertices, camera_position, camera_vec, camera_bloom = preprocess(obs)

    # if any corner of the target cube is outside of frame, return 0
    for target_vertex in target_vertices:
        if not target_visible_in_conical_bloom(target_vertex, camera_position, camera_vec, camera_bloom):
            return 0

    # if any corner of the target cube is blocked by the wall, return 0
    for target_vertex in target_vertices:
        for wall_plane in wall_vertices:
            if line_segment_intersects_truncated_plane(target_vertex, camera_position, wall_plane):
                return 0
        
    # cube is entirely within bloom and is not obstructed
    return 1
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Once we have set up the Robosuite environment with the camera and reward function, we will train a PPO agent on the MDP formulation of the \(\textit{Localization}\) stage. The image observations will be processed by a pretrained Vision Encoder, which will be frozen during training. The output features of the Vision Encoder will be the inputs to our RL neural networks. Our evaluation will consist of visualizing rollouts and establishing a success rate for the \(\textit{Localization}\) phase. A rollout will be considered a success if the object of interest is seen completely unobstructed in the scene from the perspective of the robot. In order to test for generalization, we will randomize initial states of the robotic arm, the wall, and the cube. Sometimes, the cube will be completely in view, and sometimes it will be completely occluded. It will be up to the robot to learn and decide when it needs to search around the wall and when it has the object of interest in sight.</p>

<p>Our main contributions are the training and evaluation of this first stage. Now that we have run randomized tests, we have set up a foundation to implement the second stage of our proposed method. We can simply use the final, localized state of our first stage as the initial state for our \(\textit{Task Completion}\) stage, which will also be trained using the PPO algorithm. The goal then would be to first use the \(\textit{Localization}\) stage to find the desired object behind any occlusions, and then use the \(\textit{Task Completion}\) stage to execute the task. We can then visualize rollouts of this end to end pipeline and determine the success rate.</p>

<p>This two stage training can then be compared against a baseline of training one PPO agent for the entire task from scratch. In effect we want to show that while one agent is not able to both find the object and finish the task in one go, our two step approach is able to successfully break this down into multiple steps.</p>

<h2 id="experiments">Experiments</h2>
<p>Our experimental environment is in Robosuite. We use a custom Robosuite environment, built off their Lift Environment implementation. This environment provides a target cube object, a robotic arm, a mounted camera on the robotic arm, and a table. We customize this class by adding randomness to the initial positions and orientations of all of the above objects except the table. We also add our own wall, randomized in size, positioning, and orientation. Fig. 2 shows the top down view of our experiment setup. This figure is for visual understanding purposes only and the images from this camera are not used in our training. Fig. 3 shows the first person images from our mounted camera, randomized at each initialization. We use images from this camera to train the arm to move the camera to place the target object in frame. For our training runs, we can train models with varying degrees of randomization. Specifically, in this project, we experimented with turning camera randomization on and off. For all of our training runs, we kept wall and cube randomization always on.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/fig2.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Fig 2. Examples of Top down view of randomized initialization</em>.</p>
</div>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/fig3.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Fig 3. Examples of First person view of randomized initialization</em>.</p>
</div>

<p>For our training process, we interpret the camera image using DINOv2, a vision transformer based vision encoder, and we feed the results into our reward function. This vision encoder takes in images of size 224 by 224 from the environment and outputs 384 features to our RL policy.</p>

<p>We use a proximal policy optimization (PPO) reinforcement learning algorithm that trains our model to look at the target object. We initialize our RL policy to be a 2 layer MLP with 256 activations per layer, taking the feature inputs from our vision encoder and outputing the action for our robotic arm. We configure this model through the Stable-Baselines3 library. Ideally, we would like to train our policy for 1 million timesteps, which amounts to 2000 episodes, but due to training time constraints, we begin with 200k timesteps, which amounts to 400 episodes. Further discussion of training is presented in our results.</p>

<p>Our metrics for the model that we trained are the rewards that we defined earlier. We set the episode horizon to 500, meaning that there is a total possible reward per episode of 500. A lower reward indicates that the policy struggled to find the cube. The closer the reward is to 500 the better, indicating that our policy was able to localize the cube early in the episode, and learned to keep it within view the entire time.</p>

<h2 id="results">Results</h2>

<p>For our results, we evaluate two main training runs to demonstrate the performance of our method. As we are working with a completely custom environment and task, we are evaluating the performance of an approach to a new problem formulation.</p>

<p>Initially, we trained a model on our fully randomized environment, including randomization of the cube, wall, and camera angle. The reward graph for the training of this model is presented in Figure 4. The model is trained for 200k timesteps, which is about 400 episodes, and took approximately 10 hours to train. We can see that the general trend of the rewards is upwards, with an increase in rewards at around the 130k timesteps mark. However, the rewards are also oscillating after that point, showing variability and lack of convergence to our results.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/fig4.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Fig 4. Rewards Graph for training with randomization of wall, cube and
camera</em>.</p>
</div>

<p>We wanted to demonstrate more stability within our results, so the next model we trained was without camera randomization. The reward graph for this training run is presented in Figure 5. We see an increase in rewards earlier in this graph at 90k timesteps, but then it drops again before picking up towards the end of training. Again, we see that our rewards do not converge.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/CS269-Projects-2025Spring/assets/images/group-01/fig5.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;" alt="RobosuiteEnv" />
  <p><em>Fig 5. Rewards Graph for training with randomization of only wall and cube</em>.</p>
</div>

<p>In order to test if the model converges, we decided to continue training the model with full environment randomization (camera, wall, and cube) for 1 million time steps, which took 40+ hours. Unfortunately, this training run did not converge either, and showed the same up and down performance that our shorter training runs displayed. Therefore, we see that naively training the model for longer does not improve performance.</p>

<h2 id="discussion">Discussion</h2>
<p>When we tested our model after training, we saw that our policy’s actions greatly depends on the initial conditions of the task. Since we are randomizing the environment before every episode, the initial conditions could vary from episode to episode. In the case that the wall or cube are in view in the beginning, the model performs reasonably by searching around them. However, we also see many cases when the robotic arm is pointed in an arbitrary direction away from the wall and cube. In this case, it sees just a blank white image of the table. This initial observation gives the robot no information with which to find the cube or even start searching, since that image is the only observation (we do not give the robot proprioceptive data). There is no indication within the image which way it should even search, as that would change from episode to episode due to environment randomization. We believe that this variance in the task causes instability in performance, which aligns with the results we are seeing. When there is a favorable initial condition, the model learns well, but when there is no useful information in the initial condition, performance declines and causes instability in  rewards. This performance would explain why our training graphs look the way they do, and why training does not converge simply with training for longer.</p>

<p>It is also important to note that even though we trained for 10+ hours, that only amounted to 400 episodes, which is not very much compared to other environments that train RL models with training episodes in the thousands. This increase in compute goes back to our problem setup, where we settled on the computationally expensive DinoV2 vision encoder with high resolution images, and set the complexity of our task through drastic randomization of our task environment. In future works, especially with a visually simple task environment (the only objects are a wall and cube, with no visual intricacies) it may have been better to use a smaller Vision Encoder like a ResNet or train our own CNNPolicy with lower resolution images. Additionally, we had hoped that the exploration of RL would allow it to learn to overcome drastic randomization, but through our results it seems that we were potentially wrong. It may have been better to start with no randomization and just a wall occluding a cube, and once that was working, we could incrementally add randomization to increase complexity. Once these changes are implemented, we believe that our solution could be a viable solution to the active exploration problem that we are working on.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>We present Peek-A-Boo, a two stage Reinforcement Learning framework that aims to break down any task into two stages: Localization/Search and Task Completion. We create a custom task environment with occlusions and randomization, an engineered reward function, and train an RL model with a Visual Encoder to complete the Localization stage. Through our model training, we are able to demonstrate promise in our approach through generally increasing rewards despite variability in training performance.</p>

<h3 id="future-work">Future Work</h3>
<p>Future work would focus on simplifying the task with less drastic randomization to show stable performance. Then, we can scale up to more complicated tasks. Future work could also look into other ways to stabilize the performance of the model. For instance, the Localization stage of our framework could be approached using IBRL (Imitation Bootstrapped Reinforcement Learning) [4] in order to improve stability through Imitation Learning while allowing the model to also explore the environment through RL. Additionally, another avenue of future work could be automating the reward function using object detection or semantic segmentation on the observation image. We have engineering a reward function using ground truth data, but that may not always be available when applying this framework.</p>

<p>Overall, we see this as a promising first step for active perception and occlusion-aware robotics. We are excited to see the advancements in this field to hopefully one day see robot policies that are able to explore and generalize to any extenuating circumstance that they face in their environment.</p>

<h2 id="links">Links</h2>
<p><a href="https://github.com/ophirsim/Peekaboo">Link to our codebase</a></p>

<p>Custom feature extractor using the pretrained DINOv2 base model from timm: <a href="https://github.com/ophirsim/Peekaboo/blob/main/vision_encoder.py">Link</a></p>

<p>Stable Baselines Documentation: <a href="https://stable-baselines3.readthedocs.io/en/master/modules/ppo.html">Link</a></p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>[1] Cheng, R., Agarwal, A., &amp; Fragkiadaki, K.
(2018). Reinforcement Learning of Active Vision
for Manipulating Objects under Occlusions.
Conference on Robot Learning, 422-431.
http://proceedings.mlr.press/v87/cheng18a/cheng18a.pdf</p>

<p>[2] Chuang, I., Lee, A., Gao, D., &amp; Soltani, I. (2024). Active
Vision Might Be All You Need: Exploring Active Vision in Bimanual Robotic Manipulation. arXiv preprint
arXiv:2409.17435.</p>

<p>[3] Dass, S., Hu, J., Abbatematteo, B., Stone, P., &amp; Martin, R. (2024). Learning to Look: Seeking Information for Decision Making via Policy Factorization. arXiv
preprint arXiv:2410.18964.</p>

<p>[4] Hu, H., Mirchandani, S., &amp; Sadigh, D. (2024). Imitation
Bootstrapped Reinforcement Learning. arXiv [Cs.LG].
Retrieved from http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.02198</p>

<p>[5] Liu, E. Z., Finn, C., Liang, P., &amp; Raghunathan, A.
(2021, November 12). Decoupling exploration and exploitation in meta-reinforcement learning without sacrifices. Exploration in Meta-Reinforcement Learning.
https://ezliu.github.io/dream/</p>

<p>[6] Natarajan, S., Brown, G., &amp; Calli, B. (2021).
Aiding Grasp Synthesis for Novel Objects Using Heuristic-Based and Data-Driven Active Vision Methods. Frontiers in Robotics and AI, 8.
https://doi.org/10.3389/frobt.2021.696587</p>

<p>[7] Safronov, E., Piga, N., Colledanchise, M., &amp;
Natale, L. (2021, August 2). Active perception
for ambiguous objects classification. arXiv.
https://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.00737.pdf</p>

<p>[8] Yang, J., Glossop, C., Bhorkar, A., Shah, D., Vuong,
Q., Finn, C., … &amp; Levine, S. (2024). Pushing the
limits of cross-embodiment learning for manipulation
and navigation. arXiv preprint arXiv:2402.19432.</p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Medha Kini, Ophir Siman-Tov</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this study, we present a framework for enabling robots to locate and focus on objects that are partially or fully occluded within their environment. We split up any robotic tasks into two steps: Localization, where the robot searches for objects of interest, and Task Completion, where the robot completes the task after finding the object. We propose Peekaboo, a solution to the Localization stage to find partially or even fully occluded objects. We train a reinforcement learning algorithm to teach the robot to actively reposition its camera to optimize visibility of occluded objects. The key features include engineering a reward function that incentivizes effective object localization and setting up a comprehensive training environment. We develop a simulation environment with randomness to learn to localize from numerous initial viewpoints. Our approach also includes the implementation of a vision encoder for processing visual input, which allows the robot to interpret and respond to objects and occlusions. We design metrics to quantify the model’s performance, demonstrating its capability to handle occlusions without any human intervention at all. The results of this work showcase the potential for robotic systems to actively improve their perception in cluttered or obstructed environments.]]></summary></entry></feed>